50. That's how many apps were available in
Android Market as Google Play was named when
it first launched alongside the first Android device
in 2008. A few days later, Android Market
opened for all app developers to register and
start publishing their apps without any review or
validation requirements from Google, OEMs, or carriers. For
us as developers, the ability to distribute apps and
the possibility of monetizing them through up front payments
in app billing and advertising directly to the owners of
over a billion android devices is one of the
most exciting opportunities made possible by the android ecosystem. Growing
up the dark days before smartphones and the internet,
if I wanted a new game or app I had
to go to a physical store and pay for a
cardboard box filled with floppy disks or CDROMs. As developers
a big part of our business plan back then
was how to get those boxes of our software onto
those shelves. Or in the world of mobile, how
to secure a carrier or OEM deal to get our
apps preloaded onto the devices. Today I can install
over a million apps of games created by tens if
not hundreds and thousands of developers via Google Play, all
with a click of a button. That's translated into tens
of billions of app installs. An incredible opportunity to
distribute apps to Android users in hundreds of countries.
Now, in the early days of Android, being fast
and launching first was a pretty solid strategy for success,
but as those first 50 apps quickly grew to
hundreds, thousands, and now over a million apps, it takes
a lot more than speed to stand out in
the crowd. These days the tables stakes are a base
line of quality and willingness to create great experiences
for all your users. Of course app quality can
be somewhat subjective, but over the years we've identified
the core criteria that users identify with apps of
high quality. And to make your life easier, they're
all available on the Android developer site for you
to review. This is the same checklist that the
merchandising team for Google Play used to ensure only apps
of quality are featured in their promotions and
editor's choice categories. And they include everything, from following
the app design guidelines to supporting different screen orientations,
tablets, and other devices. And of course ensuring that
your app is stable and performant. So, with over
a million apps already available in Google Play it's
no longer just a numbers game. We don't need
just more apps or games, or even more developers.
What we want is high quality apps from great developers, like you.